Danger runs deep.
Crimson Tide is a thriller, action, drama film directed by Tony Scott.
After the Cold War, a breakaway Russian republic with nuclear
warheads becomes a possible worldwide threat.
submarine Capt.
Frank Ramsey signs on a relatively green but highly recommended Lt.
Ron Hunter to the USS Alabama, which may be the only
ship able to stop a possible Armageddon.
When Ramsey insists that the Alabama must act aggressively, Hunter, fearing they will
start rather than stop a disaster, leads a potential mutiny to stop him.
Lt. Commander Ronald "Ron" Hunter, played by Denzel Washington.
Captain Franklin "Frank" Ramsey, played by Gene Hackman.
Lt. Roy Zimmer, played by Matt Craven.
Chief of the Boat Cob, played by George Dzundza.
Lt. Peter 'Weps' Ince, played by Viggo Mortensen.
Lt. Robert 'Bobby' Dougherty, played by James Gandolfini.
Crimson Tide is a 1995 American submarine action thriller film directed by
Tony Scott and produced by Don Simpson and Jerry Bruckheimer.
It takes place during a period of political turmoil in Russia, in which
ultranationalists threaten to launch nuclear missiles at the United States and Japan.
The film focuses on a clash of wills between the
seasoned commanding officer of a U.S.
nuclear missile submarine (Gene Hackman) and his new executive officer (or XO, played by Denzel
Washington), arising from conflicting interpretations of an order to launch their missiles.
The story inadvertently parallels a real incident
during the Cuban Missile Crisis.
Crimson Tide was released by Buena Vista Pictures Distribution on May 12, 1995.
The film received mostly positive reviews from critics and
grossed $157.4 million against a $53 million budget.
Hans Zimmer, who scored the film, won a Grammy Award for the main theme, which
heavily uses synthesizers instead of traditional orchestral instruments.
An extended cut, which incorporates seven minutes of deleted scenes, was released on DVD in
2006, while the 2008 Blu-ray release only includes the theatrical version.
In a 2025 interview, Bruckheimer mentioned that he was developing a sequel
and was hopeful that Washington would reprise his role.
The film explores themes of mutiny, submarine,
missile, embassy, nuclear missile.
The tone is emotional and intense.